A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews, Series Q FA352
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews, Series Q
1977-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Morrow, Hugh
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
FA352
5 Document Box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 Q
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in two subseries:
Subseries 1 - Interviews with Nelson A. Rockefeller Subseries 2 - Interviews with NAR Associates and Family Members.
Scope and Contents note
This series contains the transcripts of interviews conducted by Nelson A. Rockefeller's associate Hugh Morrow during two distinct time periods, as designated in the subseries. Morrow variously had served as Rockefeller's press secretary, speech writer, and director of communications beginning in 1960. No tapes of the interviews were saved after they were transcribed. There are no indices to the individual transcripts.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Government agencies; Federal government -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; International economic relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Business; Business enterprises, Foreign; Arts; Brazil; Agriculture -- Latin America; Art, Primitive; Education -- Latin America; Agriculture; New York (N.Y.); National security -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Developing countries; Civics; Civic improvement; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; New York (State); Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public health -- Latin America; Social problems -- Latin America; State governments -- United States; United States; Venezuela; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy; International relations; International relations -- United States
- Interviews with Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1977; 1; 1 Document Box(es)
  Arrangement note
  The transcripts are arranged in the chronological order of the interviews.
  Scope and Contents note
  Between July and November 1977, Hugh Morrow conducted 12 interviews with Nelson A. Rockefeller for the purpose of eventually coauthoring a biography of Rockefeller.
  The subject matter varies greatly both within and among the interviews. However, the topics most widely discussed by Rockefeller are his interests and activities related to Latin America and his insights on the state of the nation and the world during and immediately following World War II. Rockefeller also provides his detailed impressions of several of the U.S. Presidents under whom he served or against whom he campaigned: Franklin D. Roosevelt, Harry S. Truman, Dwight D. Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Richard M. Nixon. In the final interview (Folder 12), Rockefeller reflects on his tenure as Vice President in the Ford Administration. To some extent, throughout the interviews he also discusses his family, his childhood, and significant influences on his life while he was growing up.
  - 1977 July 12, 61 Pages (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1977 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 0001A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
  - 1977 July 14, 76 Pages (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1977 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 0002A)
  - 1977 July 19, 49 Pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1977 July 26, 64 Pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1977 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
  - 1977 August 4, 38 Pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1977 August 9, 28 Pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1977 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 0006A)
  - 1977 August 11, 16 Pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1977 August 16, 34 Pages (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1977 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 0008A)
  - 1977 August 18, 26 Pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1977 September 27, 24 Pages (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1977 October 4, 43 Pages (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1977 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 0011A)
  - 1977 November 22, 57 Pages (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1977 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 0012A)
- Interviews with NAR Associates and Family Members, 1979-1980; 2; 4 Document Box(es)
  The first 24 transcripts in this subseries are organized alphabetically by the last name of the individual being interviewed. The remaining 26 are in order by when they were opened for research.
  Following Nelson A. Rockefeller's death in January 1979, Hugh Morrow conducted interviews with Rockefeller's former associates and family members to document the memories of those people who had significant working and personal relationships with him. Between August 1979 and September 1980, Morrow interviewed 75 individuals. All but one of the interviews were tape recorded; Morrow made a transcript of the one unrecorded interview from his notes. A few interviews were summarized by Morrow, while all others were transcribed verbatim. The recording tapes were not saved.
  Currently, except for two exceptions noted below, only transcripts of interviews with those individuals known to be deceased and on which at least some editing was completed are available for research. The folder list includes the interviewees' relevant positions, dates of interviews, and page counts.
  In October 2013, Steven C. Rockefeller gave permission to open the transcript of his interview, which he edited in 2005. In February 2014, David Rockefeller gave permission to open the transcript of his interview, which he edited that same year. These are the only open transcripts from living individuals in this series.
  Throughout the transcripts, topics range from politics to art and from foreign policy to family relationships and philanthropy. There is a heavy emphasis on Rockefeller's three presidential and four gubernatorial campaigns from 1958 to 1970. A number of the interviews also focus on New York State government programs and administration. Additionally, in some interviews there is discussion of Latin America and the organizations and programs that Rockefeller established or enhanced for that region of the globe. The transcripts are most useful as indications of how these individuals viewed particular issues and interacted with Nelson Rockefeller and his staff or family.
  - R. Burdell Bixby Interview, 1979 October 3; 79 Pages (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Campaign Manager; Scheduling; Chair of New York State Thruway
  - R. Burdell Bixby Interview, 1979 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 0001A)
  - Theodore Braun Interview, 1979 November 6; 54 Pages (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1964 Presidential Campaign Advisor
  - Theodore Braun Interview, 1979 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 0002A)
  - Joseph Canzeri Interview, 1979 August 21 & 23; 139 Pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Advance man; President of Greenrock
  - Joseph Canzeri Interview, 1979 August 21 & 23 (Box 1, Folder 0003A)
  - J. Richardson Dilworth Interview, 1980 May 2; 40 Pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Financial Advisor for Investments, Room 5600
  - J. Richardson Dilworth Interview, 1980 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
  - Meade Esposito Interview, 1980 May 22; 18 Pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Brooklyn Democratic Chair
  - Meade Esposito Interview, 1980 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 0005A)
  - Gerald R. Ford Interview, 1979 November 4-5; 50 Pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
    President
  - Gerald R. Ford Interview, 1979 November 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 0006A)
  - John French Interview, 1980 January 15; 27 Pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dartmouth Roommate
  - Berent Friele Interview, 1979 November 28; 67 Pages (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Brazil office; American International Association for Economic Development
  - Berent Friele Interview, 1979 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 0008A)
  - Nancy Hanks Interview, 1979 November 19; 61 Pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Associate for President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization; Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies (Rockefeller Panel); Chair of National Endowment for the Arts
  - Nancy Hanks Interview, 1979 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 0009A)
  - George Hinman Interview, 1979 October 10; 20 Pages (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Executive Assistant; Political Advisor
  - George Hinman Interview, 1979 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 0010A)
  - Emmet Hughes Interview, 1980 April 11 & 18; 7 Pages (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Public Relations; Speechwriter. This transcript was made from Morrow's written notes.
  - Emmet Hughes Interview, 1980 April 11 & 18 (Box 1, Folder 0011A)
  - Louis Lefkowitz Interview, 1979 August 29 & September 5; 64 Pages (Box 1, Folder 12)
    New York State Attorney General
  - Louis Lefkowitz Interview, 1979 August 29 & September 5 (Box 1, Folder 0012A)
  - Arthur Levitt Interview, 1979 August 27; 23 Pages (Box 1, Folder 13)
    New York State Comptroller
  - Arthur Levitt Interview, 1979 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 0013A)
  - John Lockwood Interview, 1979 October 25; 41 Pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Legal Counsel to Rockefeller Family
  - John Lockwood Interview, 1979 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 0014A)
  - John Lomenzo Interview, 1980 February 22; 39 Pages (Box 2, Folder 15)
    New York State Secretary of State
  - John Lomenzo Interview, 1980 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 0015A)
  - Joseph Murphy Interview, 1980 August 11; 44 Pages (Box 2, Folder 16)
    New York State Tax Commissioner
  - Joseph Murphy Interview, 1980 August 11 (Box 2, Folder 0016A)
  - Kenneth Riland Interview, 1979 September 14; 97 Pages (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Physician
  - Kenneth Riland Interview, 1979 September 14 (Box 2, Folder 0017A)
  - Blanchette Rockefeller Interview, 1980 July 14; 5 Pages (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Sister-in-law. This transcript was made from Morrow's written notes.
  - Laurance Rockefeller Interview, 1980 September 24; 54 Pages (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Brother
  - Laurance Rockefeller Interview, 1980 September 24 (Box 2, Folder 0019A)
  - Isabelle Savell Interview, c. 1979; 5 Pages (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Speechwriter; Advisor. This transcript was made from Savell's written notes.
  - Thomas Stephens Interview, 1980 April 5; 13 Pages (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Special Assistant to the Governor
  - Thomas Stephens Interview, 1980 April 5 (Box 2, Folder 0021A)
  - Linda Jamieson Storrow Interview, 1980 January 4; 54 Pages (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; spouse of Public Relations Director (Frank Jamieson)
  - Linda Jamieson Storrow Interview, 1980 January 4 (Box 2, Folder 0022A)
  - Jack Wells Interview, 1979 August 14-15; 33 Pages (Box 2, Folder 23)
    1964 Presidential Campaign Manager
  - Jack Wells Interview, 1979 August 14-15 (Box 2, Folder 0023A)
  - Malcolm Wilson Interview, 1980 September 22; 46 Pages (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Lieutenant Governor
  - Malcolm Wilson Interview, 1980 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 0024A)
  - John R. Camp Interview, 1979 November 3; 56 Pages (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Paraguay and Venezuela offices; International Basic Economy Corporation; 1969 Presidential Mission to Latin America
  - Alton Marshall Interview, 1979 October 11; 70 Pages (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Secretary to the Governor; 1968 Presidential campaign; President of Rockefeller Center, Inc.
  - Alton Marshall Interview, 1979 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 0026A)
  - Ann Whitman Interview, 1979 August 14-15; 38 Pages (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Executive Assistant to the Governor; Chief of Staff for the Vice President
  - Ann Whitman Interview, 1979 August 14-15 (Box 2, Folder 0027A)
  - Harry Albright Interview, 1979 September 29; 126 Pages (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Deputy Secretary to the Governor; Appointments Officer; New York State Banking Supervisor; Special Counsel to the Vice President; Adirondacks Commission
  - Harry Albright Interview, 1979 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 28a)
  - George Dudley Interview, 1980 April 25 and May 6; 95 Pages (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Architect; Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; International Basic Economies Corporation; New York State Office of Regional Development; Pure Water Authority
  - George Dudley Interview, 1980 April 25 and May 6 (Box 2, Folder 29a)
  - T. Norman Hurd Interview, 1980 January 10; 89 Pages (Box 3, Folder 30)
    New York State Budget Director; Housing Finance Authority; Advisor to the Governor on Attica Prison riot
  - T. Norman Hurd Interview, 1980 January 10 (Box 3, Folder 30a)
  - Warren Anderson Interview, 1980 July 10; 21 Pages (Box 3, Folder 31)
    New York State Senate Majority Leader
  - Jerry A. Danzig interview, 1979 November 1; 42 Pages (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Special Assistant to the Governor for Radio and Television
  - Gus Eyssell Interview, 1980 May 20; 14 Pages (Box 3, Folder 33)
    President of Rockefeller Center
  - Jerry Finkelstein Interview, 1980 April 17 and May 13; 66 Pages (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Jerry Finkelstein Interview, 1980 April 17 and May 13 (Box 3, Folder 34a)
  - Harry O'Donnell Interview, 1980 August 9; 98 Pages (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Press Aid and Executive Assistant to the Governor
  - Harry O'Donnell Interview, 1980 April 6 (Box 3, Folder 36a)
  - Richard Roth Interview, 1980 January 9; 12 Pages (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Political Aid; former reporter for World Telegram
  - Richard Roth Interview, 1980 January 9 (Box 3, Folder 37a)